<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
  
<!ELEMENT xi:include (xi:fallback?) >
<!ATTLIST xi:include
    xmlns:xi   CDATA      #FIXED     "http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href       CDATA      #REQUIRED
    parse      (xml|text) "xml"
    encoding   CDATA      #IMPLIED >
<!ELEMENT xi:fallback ANY>
<!ATTLIST xi:fallback
    xmlsn:xi   CDATA      #FIXED     "http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" >
<!ENTITY % local.chapter.class "| xi:include">
]>

<!-- FILE   : TMLib-Documentation.xml
     AUTHOR : (C) Copyright 2010 by Peter C. Chapin

This is the documentation for the TMLib library. -->

<book status="draft">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>TMLib Documentation</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Peter</firstname>
      <surname>Chapin</surname>
      <othername role="mi">C.</othername>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Vermont Technical College</orgname>
        <orgdiv>Computer Information Systems Department</orgdiv>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <authorinitials>pcc</authorinitials>
    <copyright>
      <year>2010</year>
      <holder>Peter C. Chapin</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the
        terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or any later version published
        by the Free Software Foundation; with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES,
        with the Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST. A copy
        of the license is included in the file <filename>GFDL.txt</filename>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
    <!-- Do I really want to include this revision history? -->
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.0</revnumber>
        <date>2010-12-31</date>
        <authorinitials>pcc</authorinitials>
        <revremark>Initial release (well, not really).</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </bookinfo>

  <preface>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Trust management systems, in the context of this work, are systems that provide a
      solution to the distributed authorization problem. In a traditional system the entity that
      controls a resource, the <emphasis>authorizer</emphasis>, must maintain or access a
      database of all possible users of the system and that maps user identities to
      authorizations. When a request for access is made, the <emphasis>requester</emphasis>
      first authenticates his or her identity and the authorizer uses that identity to look up
      the allowed authorizations in the database.</para>

    <para>The traditional approach is not well suited to large distributed systems because in
      such systems the authorizer does not typically know all the potential users. Instead the
      authorizer relies on user attributes that are certified by designated authorities on those
      attributes. Specifically the authorizer writes a policy that describes the characteristics
      of acceptable users. When a request is made, the requester provides certificates that
      prove compliance with that policy.</para>

    <para>TMLib is a library of functions that allow applications to support trust management
      style distributed authorization. The core library is written in SPARK Ada for maximum
      safety and security.</para>

    <para>Managing the certificates is a significant chore in such systems. Thus this library
      provides an administrative application that can be used to create and manually verify
      certificates in multiple certificate formats. In addition this library provides functions
      for performing a proof of compliance computation that can be used in any application that
      wishes to use trust management services.</para>

    <para>The TMLib library is covered by the Lesser GNU Public License. This basically means
      that you are free to use it in any way that you wish as well as modify it as you desire.
      In addition, you can link this library into programs with "non-free" licenses. See the
      file <filename>LGPL.txt</filename> for more details. The choice of using the LGPL for this
      library instead of the GPL was made to help promote the use of the RT trust management
      system.</para>

  </preface>

  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="doc-TMLibDesign.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="doc-TMUser.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="doc-TMLibUser.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="doc-TMLibDev.xml"/>

  <!-- <bibliography> ... </bibliography> -->
</book>
